snom is to Americans as any other word
or any other concept but you know
sometimes you wonder how free we really
are in 2019 with our Apple phones and
everything else but it's there is there
is a great you'll never fun you'll never
find another love like my like mine
someone who loves you you can sing and
you play music you play piano come on
Rose put that red tan cane my father
would lord over him with a rattan cane
he forced me to play songs just beyond
my capabilities
Rachmaninoff shop on a shop on my
crucible my mistakes were numerous and
with my mistakes came the bite of the
rattan cane on my boy back again boy he
would scream yes papa I would say I
played on just gone for hours missed it
before the Clippy thing I would collapse
often he would wake me with smelling
salts when you hit the wall climb the
wall boy yes Papa Q cheetah on camera -
I have tamed this cheetah just good is
that it we can just go more insincerity
next time just dial it up yeah thanks
let's go you gonna close that fucking
door yeah this is Eric Weinstein ladies
and gentlemen Brian Kevin do you do an
Eric once that impression uh no I don't
hear or see the fit your two stayed I
think he is not yet that's right yeah
there's something about you that's very
um you're too thoughtful in a good way
say it again
so thoughtful you're a warrior of the
mind all right I have to do the head
turn okay you think I can't what is the
head turn just start hi this is Eric
Weinstein and you found the portal today
I am joined by none other than my friend
Bryan Callen Bryan welcome it's good to
be in the portal my friend yeah I'm not
worthy first of all let me say that I'm
let me apologize your guests I'm not
worthy I'm
nothing but a lowly comic athletic yes
but that's about all
supple dangerous at times giving always
well I think this is the first time
we've started with that level of
instance your groveling but thank you
Brian for breaking new territory and I
your sir stop okay now here's the thing
first of all I want to say that I so
love your conversational style that
anytime you start hosting this feel free
but we're just we're just beginning the
portal and what we're trying to do with
with the show in the series is two
separate things one I think we're gonna
have a great time being here and
interviewing lots of interesting people
but there's a sort of a theme running
through it which is that I think a lot
of people have realized that we've been
in some kind of a stasis and that some
of us may have found ways to break out
of whatever this kind of malaise or
miasma that settled over the country is
and we're trying to find the people and
the concepts that might give people some
some new options to think about how to
break free of whatever might be holding
them in place or their communities or
the country even so at all different
levels and scales one of the things that
has been most impressive to me about you
is the way you use certain techniques
for breaking new ground socially and I
was just thinking recently I happen to
be invited over to your place and you
had a group of very talented combat
sports guys just an eclectic group it
was the collective group but it was but
there was a common theme and the common
theme seemed to be people who were very
skilled in a ring or in combat like
situations and it struck me that it was
also incredibly diverse that in terms of
a diversity standard other than than the
gendered issue it was people of
different hues different religions
different cultural backgrounds different
age groups and it was one of the
greatest salons and dinners I've been to
in a long time and it consisted largely
of as the British say people taking the
piss out of each other
yeah and as a result the intimacy in the
room was off-the-charts people were
really opening up people were being
vulnerable people were actually building
each other up and somehow there is no
explanation for this behavior in the
current cultural moment it's like we've
forgotten what this is can you say a
little bit about what you think is going
on well first of all I think that it's
unfortunately most people don't think
they can make a difference with their
ideas with their conversation with their
point of view with their actions they
you know that that's that's a cynicism
it's a deep cynicism that seems to and
I've always been an optimist and I've
always thought if you look at history
it's usually a small group of people
with with a with a passionate set of
ideas that get things moving I mean
sometimes it's not for the good in my
opinion for example Russia in 1914 I
mean a very small group of intellectuals
who got the Communist revolution started
I might have been part of that back then
if you looked at the way you know Russia
was but these are people that had the
gumption and the I mean if you look at
the abolitionist movement it was really
started in in England and I think in the
1840s it started but it was about these
sort of like evangelical Christians who
said look you know no matter what we can
do this if you look even in this country
John Brown these were fanatics but they
were a small energized group of people
the Quakers they set these examples you
can even go into you know if you look
think about the ramifications of the
marriage between I think was even sowed
and maja and Wahab the marriage of those
kids and he'd they made a deal and he
said let me preach let me preach my
puritanical Salafi Islam my my
puritanical version of Wahhabi Islam
this is back in the 1700 this wasn't so
well did they met I think in 1744 but
you know Italy so this was a small group
of very energetic people now I don't
think a lot of times the outcome is so
positive and those in those instances
but I for better for worse I think the
way you beat a bad idea is with a better
idea I'm quoting Amos oz
the Israeli writer I never forgot him
when he said that and the way to come up
with better ideas yeah is not to purify
your echo chamber it's not to get it's
very tempting for guys like you and I
you know it's very exciting for me to be
able to even be you around guys like you
I love Sam Harris and you know I love
Jordan Peterson and you you're very you
you guys are very intelligent you're
highly educated and aside from the fact
that personally I like you but but it
would be very easy for all a button when
you have a dinner typically what you see
is people who've read the same books
listen to the same TED Talks yeah watch
the same programs and have a similar
background educational background I
think that's boring I think I just do
man I just love getting a Navy SEAL a
pro boxer who's never read a book uh and
then I put him with a d1 basketball
player then I get a mathematician over
there and then I get an economist over
here and then I'll throw in a
nine-year-old sometimes yeah I'd like to
do that the guy who's lived forever
who's an actor like my friend Jack Betts
and then I'll and then I'll throw in
just two two usually I'll get two people
who I know aren't gonna say much but
they want to listen you need an audience
and what you get right is idea sex yeah
got an idea orgy and people nobody looks
at their phones man and it's 1:30 in the
morning and guess what everybody's
learning from Eric Weinstein and I knew
that was gonna happen because you come
in everybody there is you know have your
arm and tighten the belly and everybody
can talk about everybody back out but
all but all of these all theses a
controlled savages are like quoting
poetry or they're talking about history
but to me and you know it's just funny
to hear you say it I you know you say
guys like you and I always felt the
comedians and the musicians and the
people who you know even study chess or
jujitsu this is all one family of people
who have you know as I've called it
before a relationship with the
unforgiving like in chess you make a
move you take the consequences the move
with rock climbing you make a
reach for bad handhold you have to deal
with whatever comes next
comedy same thing mathematics etc and so
to me there is a commonality which is
are you engaged in some activity that is
not that the where the feedback is not
mediated by somebody's choice like
there's no judge when you're a rock
climber who says well I think that was
an eight point three yeah it's the rock
yeah it's the rock yeah well I don't I
think sometimes anytime you have a group
of people that are all in the same
discipline you know the one great thing
so so you know we talk about fighting I
love to box and one of the guys there
Moloch I don't know if you remember mala
sure are tall yeah tall thin look tall
thin black guy about six 154 pounds
Mossman boxing since he was seven now
Moloch was gonna be on his way to be a
world champion he gets world champions
ready I know from other people that
Moloch gives world champions or did give
world champions fits in the gym I said
he to light him up as in he's something
special and what's fun for me is trying
to box with him and I talked trash and I
put in my mouth piece in my headgear and
I and and I I try to I cheat and I step
on his foot I kick him sometimes I do
everything I can anytime he wants he can
he can put me to sleep any time right
and he's nice enough just a padding
around and I I'm the old man I'm
swinging I try to hit him I do
everything I can to try to hit him right
when we're done he's taught me a couple
things I'm building my tree of knowledge
when it comes to boxing I love doing
anything I'm bad at because it's
humbling and somehow I think it opens
other portals you know it kind of
somehow stimulates become better at
comedy I become better at things I don't
know why and then what happens is we sit
down and he asks me because he's on this
education kick because he didn't have
the benefit of an education because he
was always boxing and so then it's time
for me to sort of tutor him as were warm
and down and we just talk over a meal so
it's a beautiful kind of symbiotic
relationship where I get so much from
him and so much wisdom and he gets so
much from me now I'm also 20 years older
she's the only reason he can beat me I
want to but the point is that they're
there so I
if I'm answering your crash question we
know you're actually getting to another
topic which I'm fascinated by you can
continue the river I can jump no please
so there's a there's a I don't underst a
degree but kind of a pattern that I've
noticed I haven't heard much commented
upon which is that social interactions
get really rich when people can pass
power back and forth in other words if
you have some kind of power and you and
you sit on it it's not nearly as
powerful as if I somehow give it away to
you and you give it back to me so for
example if you look at a happy couple
maybe the man praises his wife to the
hill talks about how he married up etc
etc and in return you know she she talks
about how you know what an honor it is
being with a man she can look up to and
the idea is that they've both exchanged
power and build something in the dyad
but okay that's a very important that's
and that's a very important idea at the
crux of why I put all these people from
different Oaks together right very
similar so so one person has 100 million
dollars the other person is having
trouble making rent what I like about
putting all those people together that
are so different is that yes yes Eric
you might be smarter at theoretical math
but you have deficits too we all do
we all do so you're you may be a
superstar over here yes mala can knock
me out with a right hand but that is
relevant only when we're in the ring
right right it's a little bit like so so
all of us have these deficits all of us
have these weaknesses where are you
smart
where are you brave where are you strong
well it depends but we are all dumb weak
cowards depending somewhere yes and so
when you try to get good at something
mm-hmm you learn very quickly what your
limitations are what your strengths are
you learn a lot about yourself and one
of the cool things about people who've
been in a ring or in a cage or on a mat
is they are very aware of how tough
they're not there is no one who you know
fight
hasn't been surprised surprised knocked
out humbled you're not getting good at
combat in which I'm not but you're not
getting good to combat with a big ego
enjoy that because what's gonna happen
is they're gonna figure you out you've
got to constantly stay humble the best
fighters are the ones the ones that I
know are the ones who are always going
back to class always learning so of
course they're gonna be humble of course
they're going to give back of course
they're going to suck my buddy I'm here
pets who is who is this like Israeli you
know badass soldier but now teaches
self-defense he's the most humble loving
giving person in the world because he
has a very very intimate understanding
of what real violence is about and how
easy it is how easy it is to take a life
I mean we're just flesh and bone so
there's no such thing as tough there
just isn't that just isn't I don't like
those words there's no such thing
probably as strong they we are all
terribly vulnerable you know I always
talk about having children and you I
hate loving something that much because
it's like watching a balloon float
around a hot lamp well we're all that
way
well you're the person actually who's
said this this is what I always tell
people about having kids the main
problem is that you don't want to love
anything as much as you end up loving
your job I mean you know thanks for
giving me something I can't bear to lose
right you know Jesus so did you get
emotional just now well yeah I mean
because I actually lived it you know I
thought about a relative who lost a son
and you know we've had two losses from
auto accidents and you see people just
transfer just transformed by a loss that
they couldn't control there's no way to
protect against then what it left me
with was this idea that nobody you're
the most enviable person in the world is
one knock on the door away from being
somebody that you would pity yeah you
know you were just saying it's so true
and so that's what that's what that's
the weird thing for me about Envy which
is I've never had a billion dollars but
I have a good friend with a billion
dollars and he's let me borrow his
lifestyle for short periods of time I
had another friend who owned an
Island and so you know he let me borrow
his Island and so I've at least seen and
felt a little bit through pretend and
play what it would be like to have a
fantastic amount of money and I wish I
could give this as a present to
everybody to just try out the lifestyle
for a day or two and figure out what it
would do for you and what it doesn't do
for you one thing it doesn't do for you
is that there's no way to keep your
children safe you can just do the
business there's no way that's that's
for sure that we are always I think
Jordan Peterson was talking about you
know in the Bible the Garden of Eden
still it's as great as it was a snake
still got in yeah I mean as even God
couldn't keep a snake out of the Garden
of Eden I mean there is always danger
lurking and you have to come to terms
with that and one of the things that I
think I like about understanding
violence at least shooting a gun right
getting knocked out getting tapped out
getting close to that a little bit I
went to a war zone you know did stand-up
in Afghanistan in 2007 but you at least
you something about it makes you feel
way more alive man you feel a lot more
alive and maybe the closer to death you
are the more alive you feel and I got to
tell you after I came back I was talking
to my buddy Dov Davidoff we were
terrified all the time because I suicide
bombings were at a high and he'd be in
these Humvees and so I started getting
addicted to that fear I mean I got I I'm
I don't want to be disrespectful to
anybody's been a combat zone but just
might a little bit I was there I think
11 or 12 days I got and then we did a
simulation a firefight with you know
lasers and stuff and I I could feel that
adrenaline
I was I was jonesing for it for a long
time afterwards and so was my friend we
talked about it you know I can't imagine
going through a real firefight you know
pgo work that he I wish and I think it
may have been Tennyson that he was
actually referencing but he he said we
used to discuss the drunk delight of
battle before we decided that war was a
bad thing and you know I'm on record of
saying that I like everything about war
except for the death and destruction
that in some sense you need life and
death
risk at least to catalyze certain things
and then there's a question about does
the life and death risk need to involve
conflict between people and one of the
things I'm curious about is the
structure of the buddy picture which is
a Hollywood staple and in the buddy
picture you have to establish the two
people really detest each other and then
they have to go through some sort of
transformational conflict and only then
do they realize that they both have sort
of a complementarity
that allows them to be truly close
that's right look what happens to guys
who who hate each other before a fight
in the UFC beat the crap out of each
other I mean they're full of blood what
do they do they hug yeah they hug well
somehow again most of the time well
there's times when no but most of the
time they hug and we want them to hug
you know I don't know that well I mean
boy there's so much to do right here you
saw this weird briefest fight in the UFC
this esperan right yeah that was
different
well it wasn't even a fight it was a
surprise attack yeah that's where hey
Maz Vito that's that's you can't talk
trash to hurt him out of it all for
three weeks before the fight the way
Askren does and then expect him not to
showboat a little bit you can't do that
to Jorge Jorge Masvidal that's a real
fight and he he still doesn't like it
like he said he goes if I see him in a
supermarket he might get slapped up cuz
I don't like yeah look so this is the
issue that some fights are
transformational and they produce a
closeness and some fights don't resolve
whatever the tension is and so one of
the things I'm super curious about is is
it your experience like if I think about
the fistfights I got in growing up I
would say that I ended up closer to
about half of the people that I fought
and it had to do with some intangible
ineffable quality I can't quite put my
finger on can you say when it is that
you find that a fight can be
transformational in male intimacy I
don't know I think I think it I think
look I mean
we are fighting is the purest of sport
in a way I mean what is football it's a
game of inches yes but it's it's
simulated war well it's like multiple
layers of indirection from war that's
right
basketball baseball these are even more
these are very I mean the competition is
very heated these guys are giving it
their all
there's something about fighting where
especially when it's MMA or something
but for that matter really boxing I
think where you where you're coming as
close as you can get almost to what it's
like to see a man kill another man or a
woman nowadays kill another woman with
their bare hands there's something
probably more deol to that that brings
us back to when we were you know when we
first evolved you know well so we talked
sometimes about the chomskyan pre
grammar of language and I've in other
places talked about the is there a
Chomsky and pre grammar of religion and
is there a Chomsky and pre grammar of
violence where whether we've we I think
we were probably communicating way
before we developed language well that's
I mean I can I can there are parts of
the world I know I can get in a fight
right away just just by holding a stare
and the way I'm standing I promise I can
get a go what's you got a problem you
want to get a fight really very quickly
I'll take you down I'll take you to
Brooklyn I'll take it along Island I'll
take you to I'll take it up anywhere in
Boston or Philly
I promise for that matter Jersey right
and and by the way not necessarily in LA
but let me take it at the Inland Empire
yeah just stand and stare for a little
bit
whereas posture up something's gonna
happen you know so we are very aware I
think we have antenna that has been have
been developed over millennia for when
somebody's trying to take what's ours
I always say this about I'm writing
about vulnerability yeah I'm writing
about what it what you know men are
supposed to be vulnerable and we're
supposed to sit with our sad and cry and
get in touch with all okay all right man
but I'm feeling point I'm dealing with a
lot of his genetic residue for a long
time you know ahead
hunt yeah you know what's with a spear
or whatever and I had to you know III
have to believe that a lot of this is
wired and and if you think of what it
was to be a human being in most cases
throughout our history whether we were
in a small village of if you were in a
vulnerable if you were in a well forget
for that matter you could have been in
Baghdad in 1258 and the Mongols are
Constantinople and what was it fourteen
something when the d ottomans broke down
the wall did our history has been here
they come over the hill they're gonna
they're gonna break down our walls and
kill us and take our women and children
as slaves right that's the story of
history you know if you'll forgive me if
I'm not a little bit ready all the time
to fight for my life what so so this is
boy am I glad we're we're here sometimes
I think about the idea that
vulnerability has to be earned through
strength so for example if you look at
Vin Diesel if he's wearing a feather boa
it's only because he's Vin Diesel he
can't wear a feather boa if you're not
really good you gotta have another man's
blood on the on the fence well you know
or you know if you ever saw what was it
with Tim Roth is this swordsman and
there's a great duel in the end is it
Rob Roy and he's like he's he's he's
there with his like Philly cuffs and
thing but he's got better sword sword
ability than anybody and he's just
completely deadly yeah and so in some
weird way in order to be comfortable
with that vulnerability you actually it
it's almost like the desert that comes
from having proven yourself as somebody
to be not to be trifled well I think
that it's an interesting thing because
when you really study the language of
vulnerability the dog and the fighters
that you know I've know enough combat
Navy SEALs and these guys I think they
have a real sense of their own mortality
I mean because they've either had to
take lives or they've seen their friend
I mean it's so it happens so quickly so
it's a combination of they become
vulnerable but they don't sweat the
small stuff
a lot of this politically correct
insanity about you said this word and
that makes you a racist or whatever it
is we're just we're so offended all the
time most of those people it goes back
to what you were saying we don't have an
existential threat anymore and so most
of those people don't really know and
haven't really suffered because they're
mostly white they haven't really
suffered this this egregious racism /
ezra klein god bless him but as you know
he I listened to him talk and stuff and
I mean Ezra is so painfully educated and
I can tell he's read every book in the
world and he lives in Washington DC and
he probably sneezed friends with all
kinds of intelligent intelligentsia and
and he can talk about how vicious
slaveholder Thomas Jefferson was and
would beat me at any debate but I don't
think Ezra necessarily really is friends
with anybody who works with their hands
who smokes or who has punch people in
the face for a living and it's not a
knock on him and I might be wrong about
him I just I I think that that his I
think if we were under in different
circumstances we wouldn't have time for
this shit we wouldn't have time for the
shit we do let me make another point
sure when I this is a better way to say
it I watch when I'm in a restaurant and
I'm and it's a busy restaurant and I see
a woman from Malaysia another one from
the Philippines and other guys black and
other guys Chinese and other bodies I
don't know what they look like there's a
wonderful composite than there - couple
white people and they're all trying to
get food to the customers I promise you
no one there is thinking about what your
sexual orientation is what your color
scheme but fuck off I'm trying to get
food on the table broke bread and this
noise this noise over here you people
are making no well that this is not fair
that it was we're like what up dude okay
good I got work to do man
I got work to do I'm making a living
here can you get the fuck away from me
and let let the economy do what it's
supposed to do right that's why
ultimately I'm a free-market guy get out
of my way with your I I don't think
we're free anymore I think we're taking
our freedoms away from it you can't say
anything
you can't express an unpopular point of
law so this would be a portal point
something I'd be super interested in
developing it for a while we started we
started hearing comedians saying I won't
play colleges anymore yeah that colleges
become unfun it throws me off my comedy
game it's not something I want to be
doing because people are so easily
offended and part of the function of
comedy was to explore that which is
offensive and to give people access
where normally they would sort of block
it off and not be able to do it and then
Joe Rogan our mutual friend said
something interesting to me he said it
is now the Golden Age of comedy I said
what
and he said well we've started figuring
out how to tell these jokes after a
period where we couldn't figure out what
had gone wrong and the best people are
now able to explore these things because
some new skill level had been unlocked
does that resonate with you as a
stand-up I don't know it's just saying
it I was thinking huh that's an
interesting thing it's certainly way
more lucrative now and it's easier to
reach a wider audience and also your own
audience so you know you can niche so
you and Joe might have different
audiences well well we may have the same
I don't know but we probably have a
similar audience but I think it's much
easier to find your niche and so that
can be a little bit deceptive okay right
so I don't know the answer he might be
right about that
I do think there's some great comedy out
there and I think it's needed I think
people like Bill burr and Jim Jeffries
and Rogen are and are needed because
they're satirist sand and it's probably
the last place on earth where you can
really speak your mind and express
unpopular points of view without
suffering the kinds of ramifications you
would if you worked at Google Facebook
or the People's Republic of Apple you
know wherever it might be these places
are pretty tyrannical it seems I don't
know I haven't worked we mentioned bill
bird so I I don't know if you know this
but I did 10 to 15 minutes of stand-up
that's all I've ever done I didn't know
that it was oh you're very funny it's
very it was very terrifying and very and
very fun but it was more or less
impromptu one of the things that I felt
as an outsider though other than that I
have no experience is that when I saw
bill burr talking about particularly
gendered issues I felt like I was
watching Alex Honnold the rock climber
go up El Capitan it was so it was so
fraught it was so dangerous course it
was um can we can we get out for a
second who is who is innovating really
new stuff and not from the perspective
of being in the audience but you know
like there there's a secret bar behind
the comedy club we were just discussing
and I was was invited back there I got a
chance to listen to water comedians
talking about in terms of craft can you
take us in to this world what is we on a
battleship Hill and rock are still doing
it they're still they're still taking on
whatever whatever say they're in
territory um I don't know that there are
I don't know that there are any
innovations I think I think the the only
the only thing you can do with stand-up
is to you know I always say write about
what you're ashamed of what you're
afraid of who you're who you're
pretending to be versus who you really
are these deeper questions how do you
want to die what do you want to say when
you die what don't you want to say when
you die you know these are the kinds of
things what do you want God to say to
you when you die if there is such a good
such a thing what if there is God and
you don't believe these are the
questions that I like to play on fears
and ask questions I think that's where
you get well that's and it goes back to
the salon thing that's where I think you
start sort of striking common ground
with our audience right so when we one
of the things I truly believe and it
comes from the fact that I lived in
seven different countries until I was 14
years old really yeah I was born the
Philippines I then moved to Calcutta
then Bombay or Mumbai and then Mumbai I
know right well it's Bombay well our
family so you know my wife and my wife
from Bombay she's the one who told me
right so she's the one who corrected me
well so right now I say mom so the weird
thing is is that it's one of these
things where educated people think that
Mumbai is the hot happening I say
sophisticated way and I think her
perspective is that that was actually
the result of the Shiv Sena who had a
Maharashtra from Maharashtrians
campaigns of Bombay sorry and he didn't
mean that people I don't know so I'm
trying to be popular well just just that
it's like New York State realizing that
New York City is captured okay and
deciding that's gonna enforce New York
State culture on New York City which is
much more cosmopolitan so Aram Bay all
right but you've lived in so the Bombay
then Lebanon then Pakistan then Lebanon
again the war broke out stuck there for
six months evacuated to Greece then
Saudi Arabia then I'm 14 years old I go
to boarding school in Massachusetts then
College down in Washington DC and then
and then of course LA New York New York
LA back and forth and finally I'm the
international movie star that I am now
well TV but but so so so my experience
right my experience being around all
those people all those Muslims and all
those Hindus and all those Christians
and all those all those Arabs and all
those Pakistanis and all those Indians
and all those Filipinos and all those
Afghan E's and all those Ethiopians and
eretrians and Somalis this is like the
12 dudes yeah and by the way in in that
I traveled to communist Russia communist
China when it really was communist
Russian Communist China Yemen Syria I
was everywhere I mean you can Jordan you
name it seeing things like leprosy
advanced stages of leprosy in the
marketplaces of Yemen I mean terrifying
things and feeling so lucky to be an
American and and and knowing not knowing
why I was never hungry but seeing real
starvation in Kenya and Tanzania and the
outskirts and and and the guilt the
fucking guilt of going what why am I so
protected why do I feel safe and so so
full of food and I'm watching you know
I'm a pretty compassionate imaginative
person I hope enough to be enough to
feel guilty right but the one thing I
got from that experience was that
essentially I don't give a shit what
your religion what your culture is
essentially we're all very much the same
we all enjoy a humorous insults we all
which is goes back to you know and we
all want a better life for our kids and
we all love to
laughs and we all want to feel safe and
all you have to do with anybody from a
different culture and I don't care where
they're from right is see them
acknowledge that they are like you
complement them a little bit maybe know
a little bit about where they're from or
ask them some questions about what it's
like to be who they are and man oh man
well the doors open and so that's why in
my salons yeah I I love proving that
over and over again by taking the most
eclectic group I can and throwing them
all together and watching all those
ideas find you know I guess life and
that's the secret well so one of the
things that I think about in this area
is how much to get this formula to work
it really requires skill and there's an
old definition of a gentleman that I'm
very partial to which is a gentleman as
someone is a man who is never rude by
accident and I think one of the problems
we're having is that there are people at
very different skill levels and so if
you think about you know the terrifying
words that one must not say that really
is sort of an admonition when everyone
is now broadcasting via social media or
their you know podcasting or Twitter
feed whatever it is that we're now
frightened that people a very low skill
and low experience are going to start
opining at scale about things that in
ways that are really destructive so for
example if you think about how far we've
come from George Carlin's observations
Carlin died right before the financial
crisis and you know his perspective was
that there wasn't a word you can't say
there are no bad words there are bad
context they're bad people there may be
bad intentions we're now in a world
where Bill Maher is lectured by a guy
who founds NWA as to what words he can't
say how does how does that shake out I
think that's just a bad idea that will
we'll be scrapped eventually I don't
know how much damage it will do the Fed
a lot of these bad ideas are repackaged
and and they will cause their damage but
hopefully because we have enough history
to draw from hopefully they will lose
their relevance I worry that there's
this there's this strange movement to go
back to old-fashioned collectivism I
mean this old-fashioned idea of
socialism and even communism and Marxism
and and I I don't know what this is
these are young people who don't and as
I really I look really pay attention to
it they don't have a command of history
they don't know a lot they just don't
maybe I'm just older and I've done more
living I lived in those socialist utopia
ISM and and I went to those countries
when they were very earnestly socialists
and communists in and I'm always amazed
that these ideas and they come out of
academia they come out of these
professors and I know a lot of them and
I've arguments with them on my other
podcast they they are people who just
don't have a lot of it I don't care how
smart you are I don't care how many
books you read you my friend don't make
the trains run on time you my friend
I've never had to make turn a profit
with a real business you live behind
walls in a university and those people
are important but they can also be just
as dangerous as somebody with no idea so
it's very would you point out and just a
riff off of that is that what if you
have a system which effectively
functions in a cult-like way which is
very few people who are academics have
ever left education in other words they
start at kindergarten or pre-k that's
what's going on and if you leave you are
it's very suspicious if you return yeah
you can't take five years off for most
people now occasionally there are
exceptions but the system as a system of
selective pressures is selecting
specifically for people who never
venture outside their initial
environment I have talked to very smart
academic all-stars people talk about
them all the time without going into
names and one didn't really realize
they were they were trying to raise some
money for something they wanted me to
host and he didn't he didn't really
understand that there were agents out
there that could raise sponsorship he
just didn't live in an economic world
but he's very happy to and we had a big
argument about it he's very happy to
advocate for an 80% tax rate for anybody
making over a million dollars because he
wants to go back to what but he thinks
to Scandinavian like socialism which is
wrong Scandinavia doesn't have that kind
of a tax rate and so you're wrong but
also this hunter-gatherer ideal okay all
right you know good luck with that but
you shouldn't be making economic policy
you're not well so you're bringing up
something which I think is terrifying
what happens when the sense making
professions that is the people that we
deputize as our experts for taking in
raw data and saying okay tell us what
this means and tell us what we should do
next and you find this in education you
find this in let's say journalism and
the the cop the sort of talking head
class all of these sort of institutional
sense makers are caught up in business
models which are now selecting for
people who have very little experience
outside of this world and I feel like if
we don't come up with jobs for that
class that pay very well what you're
going to get is you're going to get very
ideological people with very little
outside experience who are imagining a
collectivist world that functions
beautifully but not thinking about the
amount of coercion and violence that it
would take to accomplish that and
whether or not it's something you want
to even do it to begin with there's that
idea there's that saying I love which is
an idea is a very dangerous thing to
have if it's the only one you have it's
a very dangerous thing if it's the only
one you have I said and I think that
there that there is this orthodoxy this
homogenous you know kind of collective
mind that comes out of a lot of these
places and and you're right I mean
there's no room what but I have two
things to say one I think I worry that
the
a lot of these big companies I mean to
express even a different point of view
even to cite the science behind the
difference between men and women will
get you fire this because you fired I
mean it really can affect your your your
bottom line so it is a form of violence
or certainly certainly what is the word
coercion in its in in a real sense you
know the conformity must be but you know
what Americans are hard to fool and and
Americans don't like extremes and III
there is a shitload of pushback not just
in this or this hard left kind of like
mentality but it's a big pushback and a
lot of intellectual pushback as well in
my opinion and it's only getting
stronger I mean I there's a reason that
reasonable people who are responsive to
evidence like yourself like Jordan
Peterson whoever it might be there's a
reason these people really hit a chord
the people like to heat listen to them
because they're like I knew this other
stuff wasn't making that much sense you
know and I feel like I'm stuck in this
ideological world and I don't final you
guys are calling me racist who you're
calling me so you're telling me I'm not
the into equality I'm not even thinking
about that I'm a fair-minded person etc
etc so there's a lot of pushback but I
mentioned this to Sam Harris and I think
I'm going to maybe do a show on this
podcast called the Hilbert problems the
topic would be the Hilbert problems of
social justice and so maybe the easiest
one is you can't possibly understand my
experience because you don't share it
and you must understand my experience
because it's so important and so you
just take these two things and then you
say look I want to discuss those that is
a couplet
I must understand and I cannot
understand because that's your problem
after all and what if I can actually
write a screenplay let's say or do an
impression on a stage where you say that
was so good that there's no way you
could have inhabited that character
without understanding I felt that way
for example if you remember Eddie Murphy
is the old Jewish guy I mean he does it
better Jew than any shoe I know of
course he does
he's an actor and he was around them and
you know exactly right actly
and so this idea that again it goes back
to what goes back to the fact that we
have a lot more in common with each
other than we well in order to in order
to unlock that though don't we have to
have enough safety to and this is kind
of this puzzle for me about the weird
social justice movement if you create
canceled culture you're telling me that
it is not safe to open my mouth and say
something that's right your ideas are
harmful therefore I'm not going to even
bring them up to a conscious level
because they're far too dangerous what
if one of them came out of my mouth and
advertently or inadvertently distributed
everybody has it that's probably I mean
I I have multiple feelings about how I
feel about different people in different
circumstances if you don't allow some of
this stuff to bubble up and come out
your mouth and look at it for the
brainfart that it really is yeah then
you're you're going to sit there
weirdly guilty I'm either angry that you
can't say that you want to be able to
say it yourself or you're gonna say wow
I really am ashamed that I actually I
always say we'll all of us in my think I
had to choke all of us have at least ten
thoughts an hour maybe a minute that
would get us fired I mean and thank God
by the way thank you know Jonathan hight
I don't have you've heard him talk on
this subject but he wrote the copling of
the American mind and the righteous mind
he's just I love him and and but he said
that there is this he compares it to the
I think the corazon of the Philippines I
think that's where they were called who
would gain status by killing the most
people you know essentially your enemy
and you take their heads or you take us
trophy maybe a piece of their hair and
you gain status that way you got more
women that way and this is an example of
a Sikh culture I don't give a shit how
how pure it is it's a Sikh culture right
and there are a lot of examples of that
and
we seem to be in some pockets of this
country there is this this you gain
status by finding the racist by finding
the the bad guy according to your
orthodoxy according to your puritanical
your Puritan but guys you have what a
human being should be it's an in
scavenger hunt that's gone out of
control like Pokemon for bigots in there
and it's it's like new though it's a
form of the inquisition it's not new
this is this again human beings love
purity they love the idea you get these
people who love the idea of trying to
purify and create their own utopia which
a lot of historians have written about
the most dangerous thing a human being
really a gross dangerous thing a
movement can endeavor to do is to purify
or create a utopia because what you'll
do and if you have any questions see
Mao's China Pol Pot's Cambodia Stalin's
Russian style I would have people killed
because they had the wrong idea of what
communism and then you take whole groups
because they've already been corrupted
their brains you can't really riad you
get them they're too old so they're all
wearing glasses anybody who's wearing
glasses is an intellectual they read a
lot they have a lot of this poisonous
capitalist stuff in their head let's
just bring them out of the killing
fields and let's get rid of them that's
what happened throughout history that's
what happens when you have ideologues
running things because they're not smart
they're fanatics they don't open
themselves up to other points of view I
don't know why nobody ever talks about
it's exactly what you're saying this
issue that purity is weirdly the most
dangerous concept we have when people
try to purify terrible things happen and
we have a ritual on Friday nights we
have a weekly Shabbat dinner and in our
family we we take the Shabbat a cup of
wine and we put two drops in it and
there's always this question why do you
put two drops of water and the wine
beforehand my interpretation is that it
is us learning to live with impurity
that these two drops of water can bother
your mind well now now the wine isn't
pure it's been add watered-down its
adultery it makes no effing difference
to the wine and it's teaching my the way
I view it is it's teaching my children
to avoid becoming fanatics about purity
when I think about the off-ramp I don't
know if you've ever seen this in Saudi
Arabia on the road to Mecca there's this
wonderful off-ramp that says Muslims
only Mecca this way all others this is
your opera yeah and I think about that I
think wow I wonder how much of the the
the division in Islam between things
that go towards this jihadist craziness
and the things that make for this
wonderfully rich welcoming culture some
in some ways they're inextricable but I
wonder how much of it has to do with
which portions of the culture have
learned to live with impurity well I
look at our culture Thomas Jefferson
owns six hundred human beings when he
wrote all men are created equal that we
hold these truths to be self-evident
that all men are created equal and
endowed - that created certain
inalienable rights among which are life
liberty the pursuit of happiness
he owns six hundred human beings when he
wrote that I mean we we our peculiar
institution I mean slavery we've been a
country with slavery longer than when
we've been a country without slavery but
you'd be hard-pressed to find a freer
longer standing democracy throughout
history we are a modern country
precisely because we continue to wrestle
with that inconsistency so this is
something I'd love to dig in to one of
the weird things about hearing the
patriarchy of the patriarchy picture is
the one place that was an actual
patriarchy was the founding of our
country and what's hysterically funny
and just sort of beautiful about it is
that the these guys wrote with enough
generality that they didn't make the
mistake of saying all men other than
Africans are created equal or all men
are created equal and not you women they
spoke with a level of generality we're a
general life liberty and the pursuit of
happiness is think about that right you
have the right to life you have the
right to liberty and you have the right
to pursue happiness not happiness but to
pursue a meaning struggle if pursuing
happiness is is I don't know living in
water in a pond whatever it is then
that's you have that right right and
that is that's how a real religion
that's that
it's what we come to defend you know
woman that's his right
you better it but the theory in some
sense was so much more advanced than the
instantiation at the founding of the
country one of the things that I find
hysterically funny and also hopeful is
that we we have the opportunity in this
country and we don't do it much to teach
both every lousy stupid hypocritical
thing we've done as a nation many of
them violent many of them deadly
and to teach patriotism on top of that
because if you think about this in terms
of all countries have histories which
contain things that they'd rather sweep
under a rug and somehow patriotism has
been sort of try people on the right
really try to take it over and as a fan
somebody comes from a very progressive
family which suffered because of let's
say the McCarthy era I love this country
and I know every lousy thing it's it's
ever done yeah do we have an opportunity
to sort of reboot patriotism at a more
mature level where the love of one
country is an adult love rather than a
childlike love I think that most people
I happen to believe that most people are
patriotic for the right reasons I think
America is an idea I mean the founding
fathers solve the political problem
the Greeks couldn't do it and no one
else could do it the Ottomans couldn't
do it the Roman sure as hell couldn't do
it this was this is I mean these are a
bunch of men in their 30s with the
exception of Benjamin Franklin got
together what was in our hot July in
Philadelphia right and came up with this
thing called the Constitution and the
Bill of Rights are you fucking kidding
me I mean think about it for a second
it's insane it's it's it's astonishing
checks and balances you've got a you've
got a Supreme Court and I mean and it
was what was I legend goes you know what
when Ben Franklin came out and she's the
woman said what have you created he said
a Republican madam if you can keep it
yeah
it's great but this is this is an
experiment this is a verb it has to be
constantly defended George Washington
said careful or human beings will invent
ways to take their own freedom away from
themselves in the name of virtue and
everything else so I think that for the
most part what I appreciate about
patriotism in this country mm-hmm and
you know is is the that at least people
truly believed that we stood that
democracy having a say right and who
governs you and and and the big question
in political philosophy who governs the
governor well in our case it's the
people now I know we can get into you
know lobbying and how we're losing that
ability and special interest of course
but for the most part that is always
what's fiercely debated you know we are
worried always that Washington is
becoming an economy of influence that
that that we are losing our meritocracy
but but it's still the fact that the
look at how vicious the press is to
Donald Trump and amen to that whether
you like him or not you never want to
lose the ability to this constant nasty
battle oh I want to take issue with this
actually the first place where I might
have a district okay but this nasty
battle this nasty battle between that's
fake news you're full of shit he's a
scumbag he's a sex addict all these
things he's a rapist I don't think
actually it's ever been any different in
in American politics American politics
has always been what would they day used
to compare Abe Lincoln to an ape and all
kinds of things and they try to start
all these sexual rumors about different
Canada this has always been a dirty
place but I think that's probably what
you get in a vibrant democracy the big
difference the big difference between
our democracy and someone else's let's
just take it on yeah is if the
hardliners lose they die they don't live
to fight another day when we lose a
peaceful transition it's a peaceful
transition so if it's incredible and and
the big
the big thing was I think with between
Jefferson and John Adams I think John
Adams wanted a standing army and
Jefferson was against that
and-and-and but it was them look they
were very worried that they called them
these wild-eyed Jeffersonians I mean
they were very worried that Jefferson
was come back to this agrarian utopia
and I mean he was a kind of a there was
a lot of talk about we gotta get rid of
these this is this could be a civil war
I mean anytime you have a Revolutionary
War anytime you have a country that wins
their independence almost like always
they break into a civil war the tube
somebody's gotta fight for power this is
the this is the only country I can think
of yeah that didn't have that happen and
so III don't know where how we got along
on this but but but it you mean so like
Indian Pakistan during partition after
all very high yeah a horrible a horrible
Civil War right and if I the created the
formation of Pakistan right but so so
there's something very special about
about our patriotism about our democracy
as messy and as nasty and as
quote-unquote partisan as it is maybe
it's supposed to be that way
maybe maybe government is supposed to
move at a snail's pace well I think when
you have some I think we're in a very
dysfunctional period where the amount of
nonsense
you know I refer to K fabrication from
the word kayfabe which is the system of
Lies that professional wrestling uses to
tell its stories right so you've never
heard that but I like it yeah yeah so I
do I do have to say before you go into
your thing I love when you come up with
these things because when you left the
dinner
Maalik a professional boxer from you
know Louisiana and Vegas and my buddy
Herman who played d1 ball and he's from
Philly and
both of them both of them were like not
fuck with Eric I fuck with that dude
he's so fucking smart he was saying shit
I wanted to oh we have another dinner
without dude like everybody one or more
Weinstein when your wife by the way
she's a superstar she's she's great
she's she's fantastic but keep calling
we got to get around the show the when
it comes to kick to kick to K fabricate
a fabrication I think that we're in a
period of nonsense
we're we're talking about all sorts of
things and the best that can be said of
us is that we are inefficient in
unraveling ourselves what I worry about
is that we actually need something like
an enemy in order to remind ourselves of
how to get along despite our differences
and I don't know whether part of the
problem is that this unprecedented level
of peace even with foreign entanglements
since world war ii is in fact deranging
us is that possible I I do I've heard
that theory right I've heard I've heard
that sort of without war I think it was
the British general I cameras Nana said
without war you know the population
becomes very materialistic and petty and
until you have a common enemy that's
what unifies the country and gets people
back down to what's actually important
values duty honor things like this I
don't know I think time I think time
will tell I think there's a there are a
lot of challenges there's enough you
know you were talking about combat
athletes and you know all these guys I
think you said something so far I feel
like I was on the Serengeti with a bunch
of thoughtful cheetahs over a kill who's
the fucking greatest metaphor ever heard
it was so great but what you forget is
that all of us think of you as the alpha
male no but it's true because you come
in there and you're not physical but
you're funny is everybody here you're
just cracking everybody up but then at
the same time everybody knows everybody
knows you've got the biggest brain in
the room so we started asking you you I
asked you about string theory it was so
fucking hilarious cuz you started
talking and all of us are like I don't
know what he's what's he talking about
well you know well the loops if you look
at the loops in the cones of the sphere
we have a predator I'm like what the
fuckin hey bro in in English stop with
the Greek you're speaking already what
there was there was a fair amount of
wine there was a fair amount of there
was me but the point is is that you had
your own alpha status there so there was
a there was a very you know what do you
want to get into what I wear them the
bumps are to tie that back in it's hard
it's it's hard enough I don't know that
we necessarily need an existential
threat trying to make it in this economy
and trying to put food on the table and
gain some leisure time is still as hard
as it ever has been so maybe that's I
don't know I don't know I don't know the
answer I don't know the answer either
but I do think that one of the things we
need to get back towards and just
riffing again from the ways in which I
was observing your crowd deal with stuff
is twice I've been in a social gathering
with you where there's been one female
and a bunch of these guys and I've
watched how careful all the men are to
elevate not only the female but whoever
is there with the lone female in the
group and the idea being that when it
when it when it was my wife the idea was
people were were holding me up and being
a little kinder and a little nicer
because you want to make that person
look good in the eyes of the woman at
the table and they're really astute
observation I think I agree with you
that's exactly what was happened well
because because in my mind we've gotten
we've broken something a little bit in
terms of male-female relations and we
are going to be in a process of either
rediscovering what was lost or ree-ree
instantiating whatever the abstraction
was that was chivalry do you have any
thoughts on on where that goes
like for instance look my experience
with the men I know that I'm friends
with and the hardest toughest guys but I
know and stuff like that they're all
gentlemen you know you if if you have a
guy who's not being a gentleman who's
rude
yeah through the woman at the table or
who is making her feel embarrassed or
oncome that that guy's not in our
fucking group when you're first gonna
correct like
oh you man you corrective signal oh and
all of my friends what I think is super
important and attractive about chivalry
is the idea of protector
well if protector that that there is a
functionally important role I'm gonna
try to figure how to get at this thought
to the violence that is you know if
there's a knock on the door for example
at 3:00 in the morning my model is is
that mom goes to the nursery and dad
goes to the front door to handle it
correct sir and that there is an
expendability of us males that we accept
as part of this bargain that children
and that's in our DNA it's in our DNA
right you're the first line of defense
you're the first and last line of
defense
that's 100% the case and I I don't
apologize for that and I don't have a
friend that's not that way that's that's
we want to be the and that's attractive
and that's Noble that's beautiful and
that's men at their best by the way yeah
that's what people don't realize when
you talk about I always say this man I'm
I you know when we talk about gun
control right I don't like gun student I
don't like them and I don't want spree
shooters out there and I think III
listen hard to people who are pro-gun
control because I want to find a
solution for us insanity okay but people
have to understand that men like myself
who own guns and have them in the house
right I don't own guns because they're
shiny and they go power right I own guns
because they make me feel like at least
if the shit hits the fan
worst-case scenario every course I can
protect the people I love yeah that is
so deep in me man and and that's what
it's about so so give me a little credit
I may be a caveman yeah
but I'm trying to be the best caveman I
can be man you know it's also like the
other thing is they you can be a dirtbag
but don't be a dirtbag you can be a
dirtbag yeah you got a lot of girls you
know
but if you are if you are hurting
people's feelings right humiliating
people III tell you man I had a good
friend and he had he got gonorrhea yeah
and I call I said to him because hey do
you have a doctor do I need these pills
I go okay good
I go make sure you got to tell the girls
cuz the girls you were with he was with
like five girls it right they can get it
in and they can go Baron right and he
said I'm not doing that when he said
that right I call it the click I called
the click I go you can have sex all of
them right but now now you're risking
someone's ability to have children dude
right and and it's embarrassing you got
to make the call and when I realized he
wasn't gonna make the call I never I
couldn't do it I couldn't I never spoke
that was it that's it you're out so
that's that to me is chivalry well so
you don't have to be perfect but just
take care of your weight bro right so
one way of looking at that is that let's
imagine that there are a group of men
and a group of women who both sort of
sign up for this kind of an agreement
like in the story that I was saying
about the knock on the door I perfectly
believe that Mommy should go to the
nursery with a shotgun if she's worried
that somebody's gonna come barging in
you know it's not a question of women
should be defenseless it's a question of
the first line of defense and who's
expendable and this is just part of the
deal and I understand if some people
don't like that they don't believe in it
but those of us who do believe in that
model should be able to locate each
other as a culture and say hey this is
the compact that that we're interested
in perpetuating by the way you know I
talk and I'm sorry to bring up my
special again but in complicated Apes
this last thing I I talk about how I'm
always amazed that the women's movement
hasn't spoken more about the women of
the UFC I do this whole bit about the
idea that I did not expect women are
moving into this space and they're doing
it very effectively if you had told me
eight years ago that I'd watch women
throw hands and feet and elbows and
grapple
with the same skill and ferocity as men
I would have I would have told you
you're crazy I would have said they're
not biologically capable or that
interested or that interested and then
you watch Rose namajunas Johnny and Jen
Jack Valentina Shevchenko Amanda Nunez
Holly Holmes I can keep going down the
list
Misha Tate's no longer work around a
Rousey Ron Rousey you know she might
have gotten out knocked out by Holly
Holm she will go down in history as the
very significant woman who was beautiful
and also fierce she kind of redefined
what she said it was the greatest thing
I ever heard she goes my body's not
designed to fuck millionaires this is
designed to beat the shit out of people
and it was like Amen sister she's one of
the first people I've ever been
starstruck in front of I was just you
know she was choosing my audience one
time then and and I I didn't I didn't
perform well I was I've never done that
I was nervous I was like so I was so
fanboy doubt but these these women are
are proving to as far as women that are
changing hearts and minds the ones that
need to be changed like a bunch of bros
like myself etc yeah the guys out there
who thought that this arena belonged
only to men there they have changed our
minds and let's talk about LGBTQ or
whatever let's talk about Amanda Nunez
whose girlfriend is in our corner yeah
kisses her girlfriend her girlfriend's
hot and she's a fight or two you got a
couple of lovers kickin ass and changing
the world I mean this is this is why are
we not talking about violence against
women when it's done by another woman in
a cage goes a long way and changed in
the heart and mind of a chauvinist like
myself who we should be talking about
man and nobody's talking about that
because of course they don't watch the
UFC well but it's also you know just
there's a confusing aspect which i think
is good confusion how many of these gals
when you see them doing you know their
what do I call the pre-fight wedding the
way I understand well there's okay the
staredown not the way in the other
things way and then you do the stairs
then you do the stair down how many
times if I looked at these gals in the
stair down said those are two really
super attractive super feminine
attractive
and yes and both of them could rip my
head oh my god Valentina Shevchenko's so
hot to me
misha takes so hot to me right they're
all so hot I mean that the majority of
them are physically beautiful they're so
attractive to me right I mean it's it's
it's like you're just like are you
kidding you you have this skill set and
you look like that I've seen them I've
seen you know cat Zingano I know some of
them I've actually gotten to move around
a little bit and train with some of them
and and it's just like they're they're
beautiful
well also it you know it calls men to
higher purpose as if one of the great
things that could come out of this is
that if men want to retain some sense of
you know being the protector that
they're gonna have to up their game and
that's the and that people are gonna
have to you know raise better boys well
that's going to be inevitable I think
you you have I I will say I have this
sort of visceral reaction to the
feminist movement because I'm a guy and
it's not my generation and I it makes me
feel insecure and stuff but there is
something really cool about women
stepping into these spaces and maybe men
can take a breather you know you know
Esther Perel at all know that name she's
sort of a next-level relationship ex I
know I asked her oh yeah yeah yeah I was
hanging with her and she was trying out
an idea which I thought was was pretty
good what she said
I was trying to she said I yes sir I was
trying to figure out masculinity what I
realized is that masculinity is both
incredibly powerful and incredibly
fragile and that comes with a lot of
fear men are very are terrified
terrified they'll be refused to be a
coward
we're terrified of every aspect I mean
well we don't sit and sad we're not
allowed to sit and sad right so women I
think have more license so they're
allowed culturally sit in sad to cry to
feel and to eat ice cream or whatever it
might be men are we can be sad for a
couple minutes then we have to convert
that sad to action ray right or target
it toward the person or thing making us
sad and attack and kill it and I I think
I feel that very very deeply and
directly I think that's been that has
been what I've had to deal with my whole
life I hate to say it but that's but
that's been handed down to me do you
accept
I'm as I get older I'm trying to wrestle
with having a relationship with that
side of me you know yeah my father was a
Marine my father you know he told me a
story recently about when you say you
know visiting war memorials he went to
Iwo Jima and I think only if you're a
marine you're allowed to and you can go
there's one day here I think when when
people are allowed to walk the island
and he was there and or family of her
maryam something and he was there and an
old woman she was about 90 she was
walking on the beach and she was having
trouble because the sand is very deep
and it's volcanic and and he said can I
help you
what brings you to the island and she
said my husband was here and he was 19
he was killed and and she said she said
I always wanted to walk where he died I
always wanted to walk and I'm walking
this whole perimeter so that I can feel
like I stepped where he was I don't know
where it was but at least I'm there you
see how you get emotional - yeah what
one my father told my story I got I
started to get emotional yeah but I
couldn't do it in front of him I
couldn't I couldn't cry but they're just
telling you that story makes me want to
cry
yeah because it's just it was so it was
such a beautiful thing my father walked
her all the way across the island or you
know or wherever that was man and and
there are some things worth crying about
like and this is one of this is one of
them you know some things are just too
much to bear and and some things are too
beautiful and some things are too they
just they just remind you of how awesome
and awe-inspiring humanity can be and
and what happens in the face of terrible
tragedy that's sort of bonding the
beautiful stories the beautiful stories
of of that's why I studied Nazi Germany
I was my area of focus and
yeah and so when you when you when you
hear about the girl whose sister it was
her birthday and she found a blueberry
in the fields they were having to work
and she wrapped it in a goddamn leaf and
gave it to her sister for her birthday
those little things man those little
things are what we stay alive for and
those stories about those little things
are probably why a lot of us are artists
you know trying to figure out a way to
get people to laugh and cry that's
that's the whole deal that is our
respite from from this constant this
drudgery this tragedy this uncertainty
this fear it's what it's what
Schopenhauer and especially Nietzsche
talked about is that yes there's the
will we've got to sleep eat fuck run and
then we die but there are there isn't
there is a way out there there are
portals if I may those are artistic
inspiration and conversations like this
and great meals with friends have salons
and that that's what we stay alive for
and you can turn your life into a circus
now you may die young and leave a
good-looking corpse right but I'd rather
that I'd rather live dangerous and not
have enough transcendence on the
distance fuck yeah yeah and you can't do
that
you can't do that living in this
purified echo chamber in a world where
you're terrified to insult offend
everybody Under the Sun you won't have
the kind of sex you want you sure as
hell won't have the kind of laughs that
you need and that you deserve you'll
live in a sexless barren place
where you're constantly trying to be
right and not offend anybody you won't
even be able to raise your fucking voice
and I think that's bad for us well they
think it's bad for our culture you know
if somebody put that to music please
they will I know you can't believe you
didn't start playing the harmonica
something right here I know you know I
was going to potentially open this
series with my cousin ooh
her name was Eva Kor and I spoke to her
right before we launched I guess the the
portal and she said look I'm going on my
annual pilgrimage
and when I get back I'd love to and
she's from Indiana I never met her I've
spoken to her a bunch on the phone and
she was a Mangala twin and her sister
Miriam was in the camp with her she was
saying that she looked forward to an
annual pilgrimage to Auschwitz where she
was and that Miriam her sister had
stopped thriving in the medical
experiments and the only way to save her
was to steal food to the point about the
the blueberry had a sister so she stole
potatoes and she was telling the story
about stealing potatoes and that the
penalty for stealing potatoes was death
yeah and so she stole these potatoes and
got caught so she was clearly gonna die
and then she was scolded and like let go
now she was just a little kid and she
said huh being part of the medical
experiment means I'm protected by dr.
Mengele and so nobody can touch me so
she continued to steal potatoes in order
to save her sister and she's telling me
this crazy story and I think I'm gonna
do an episode because she it went to the
extraordinary length of forgiving
Mengele and this caused a huge human cry
and it was Eva Kor and I was dying to
start the podcast and then I get this
phone call from her son
and I find out that she's died in Poland
on this last trip Wow so I don't get to
bring the story the way I wanted to yeah
man was this chick tough Oh left you
know the whole idea anyway when I tell
the story I think I'll do it on a
separate episode of the importance of
forgiveness and as a almost like a
weapon and as a structural
transformative ritualistic option if
you've been victimized this woman gave
nothing up in terms of toughness and
then went to these
ordinary counterintuitive lengths one of
her last posts I think is her eating
maybe a McDonald's meal in Auschwitz and
sort of laughing about how amazing that
there's a McDonald's near where we had
automated human ritualistic killing
Frank you know and Frank I think she
wrote I still believe in my heart human
beings were all good at the core right
you know and her father said she shames
me with her is it positive you know
outlook but I I think that's the that's
probably one of the reasons Christianity
seems to endure the idea that Christ
preached forgiveness that's a powerful
thing what you're really saying I mean I
know right as an actor for example you
know I had an acting teacher as an actor
if you're playing man quit right if
you're playing Pol Pot Stalin or Hitler
really can't play him like a monster you
know you play them you play him as a man
trying to solve a problem for Humanity's
sake that's way more interesting and
that very well may be what was going on
in their twisted hearts even the Nazis
had had a sense that they were doing
God's work that they were being somewhat
more alone getting rid of this problem
called the Jews etc and this is why
ideas and if you just rely on logic and
rationality you better be careful man
because human beings come up with very
very logical and rational reasons to get
rid of those people over there
it's one of the things I love about what
the thing that religion has to offer
which is that all life is sacred the
Buddhists talk about sentient speech
ensign said sentient beings the
Christians talk about you know whether
or not you're in a coma
even if you're unborn listen you know
these these things they're and their
unwavering about those things sometimes
that is the vanguard sometimes that is
the reason you have to be stalwart in in
in in those kinds of ideas they're not
convenient a lot of times I'm a
pro-choice guy but I understand the
value of these kinds of things because
they do protect you against you know the
rationalists come in the scientists the
engineers who come in and start trying
to run the world well don't trust your
own brain I think it was Paul Paul
don't trust your own heart yeah I'm not
a Christian by the way yeah but no I'm
not I haven't been to church I don't go
to church I've been to church twice in
my life but I I respect and understand
what these fixed truths have to offer
it's my only contention with Sam Harris
who I really like and I admire but um
I'm gonna give Sam just a quick lesson
if I ever meet him on how not to how not
to start a conversation Sam don't say
let's we have we need a war on Islam
don't say that right you can't do that
because you lose everybody we got to we
got to be a little bit more we got he's
he's so he's so painfully honest we you
know I went on his show about this point
no you know I didn't okay so I did it
but but I'm a fan so you know but I'm a
fan of Sam's - I mean you were great
friends I tried to indicate to him that
there was something counterproductive
not about his line of thinking but about
his chosen motive of expression he does
motional obviously Sam gets emotional I
think that's what it well but any
sublimated right yeah so you know you
almost never see him video mind its way
through I took a video of him playing
centipede on an old arcade machine and
people loved it because they said oh my
god he's human he's very he's very zen
even a very human yes the issue that I
had was that I didn't think that Sam
understood what he was projecting and
that I said you know you need to say
some things about the positive aspects
of this culture well it was like you
open up this box he's like I love the
call to prayer I said what it's like I
love the poetry of Rumi and so he starts
extolling
some of the some of the advantage so
he's an incredibly religious guy for an
atheist I mean I I do his app waking up
yeah I love this book spirituality
without religion right I love his
podcasts and I and I think that he's
genuinely sincere about trying to get an
honest conversation going I fall in line
with so much of his thinking but I do
think that he I know I do think he could
he could he I think he does I think he
gets emotional yeah I think then he goes
on the offensive and that's he's very
upset about people not understanding his
central message I think it whew
few people understand what it is he is
not claiming is that Islam is it's a
terrible thing that it has nothing to
offer he's not claiming that religion is
bereft of good ideas or important ritual
what he's weirdly saying doesn't get
picked up is i sam harris believe that
there is nothing that can be done
irrationally through a crazy belief
system that couldn't be done better at
scale using reason but that's great
i agree i think you've all her re would
disagree
you need myth you need story and and and
so so so the value therein let's just
take christ as an example sure bible or
any story or even plato's forms were
about the idea that you may not be able
to touch perfection but my god you can
imagine it you did perfection may very
well not exist but you can not only
imagine it but you should reach for it
you're gonna miss but the reach is what
matters so so doing the right thing a
lot of times might be very much against
not in your own interests i mean think
of the play The Crucible well I mean
he's going to die for Christ's sake but
he's not going to give up his you know
he's more than his appetites rise more
and the man for all seasons these are
these stories that we think about the
the Mohandas K Gandhi Martin Luther King
Malcolm X Jesus Christ with a these
people in juror and they way we speak of
them and sort of with heads bowed
because they put their own interests it
was not there was nothing rational about
what they did in a lot of ways I mean
you could say it was well well I mean
they they they knew that they were
putting themselves to matically they
were definitely putting themselves in
you drift a exterminate a they erased
themselves physically but there's
something about if you ever read Gandhi
on violence yes a long time ago yeah you
ever seen this riff that he did where he
said there are three things I want to
talk about I want to talk about pacifism
I want to talk about violence and I want
to talk about non-violence and he says I
believe that my philosophy of
non-violence is superior to the other
two but given a choice between violence
and pacifism I would always choose
violence I don't remember that
I know hero was his a huge influence on
him it's so Gandhi the Gandhi that we
think of as the simple kindly saintly
figure is not actual Gandhi and Gandhi
was an Anglophile I know he's a lawyer
in South Africa who yeah well there's
that yeah
but he actually believed he said look
don't mistake non-violence for pacifism
non-violence requires the most courage
because you're going to put yourself in
harm's way with a pre commitment not to
defend yourself and if you can't get to
that level of badassery choose violence
and why because the worst thing you can
do is to be passive and to let your
nation you know be raped as India was by
the Brits so this is like ye may have
been a strategic cuz I don't think that
that policy of non-violence would have
worked against the Nazis the Germans
would have just shot him and they would
have just opened up on anybody it worked
with the British Empire because the
British Empire had elections they had
Parliament there's a question of who
does who does the non-violence and I
don't know if you know about the Rosen's
stress of protest terms you want to talk
about weird portal effects mmm
I think was 1943 in Berlin a bunch of
women who were married to Jewish men or
partially Jewish men but were not Jewish
themselves decided that they would show
Nazi Germany what's what and get their
husbands back and they organized to
protest I don't know why this isn't
famous it makes me feel like I'm crazy
for bringing it up they organized a
protest in the Rosen Strasse of the
street and they made such an
embarrassing show in front of the Nazis
that the Nazis I believe acquiesced and
got these men out of the camps and
returned to the women so it was like a
Wow well this is the thing about the
power of wives and mothers and beautiful
young women you know who are you know
nubile just means marriage able
we are so when women organize themselves
effectively they can bring mail systems
you know really to their knees because
there's no good way of saying we're
against motherhood were against love
were against anything that is
aspirationally kind of pure yeah
somebody's drug people have drawn
correlations between women's rights and
healthcare and the advent of health care
and things and which is why the marks
was so confusing to me because that was
a tremendous amount of power to mobilize
but without a very clear follow-through
and with some very dubious you know I
think that a lot of us fear that there
was some kind of anti-semitism that was
behind some of the organization of that
but just in terms of what could you get
the Nazis to take note of I've always
been fascinated by who protested the
Nazis effectively there was another case
which you might know through through
boxing I think the guy's name was
johannes trollman
who was a Sinti like a roma and he was
incredibly good-looking and he was doing
the Muhammad Ali thing years before
Muhammad Ali of being very athletic as a
boxer so is kind of a matinee idol of
this time and Germans were fantastic
audiences for boxing they were very well
informed about the sort of science of
the sport and obviously this guy had to
go down because he wasn't pure an Aryan
in German but the crowd the Germans
loved him yeah and when he was I guess
they're you know the the refs gave the
fight to the other guy there was an
outcry in Germany hmm so they changed
the rules about how you could fight and
it was to make this guy's fighting style
not work so as a protest I mean just
this is such a great story he divorced
his wife because he thought it was a
danger to her Wow
he coated himself in flour to mock the
purity of this you know racially pure
German right yeah and he got into the
ring with the crowd behind him and he
took the effing loss Jay right
get sent to a camp and everybody
Revere's them it's like you know the
South Africans respected Nelson Mandela
well did not cease fucking respected
this guy and well they Germans at least
yeah even the Nazis yeah
you know because in some sense they know
that they're doing the wrong he can kick
their ass you know it's what you just
said about fragility like here's this
guy who is a genius with his fists who's
this unbelievable figure in his heart
and what is he doing
you know he's mocking them and he's
sacrificing his own life so he ends up
in the camps he's he's holding fighting
clinics and I think somebody kills him
with a shovel or a pistol or something
so it's a terrible story there's a ring
in a park in Germany on a slant and it's
just the slant is the unfairness of the
situation right Wow and he was
reinstated his title had been taken away
and it's been reinstated all these years
later somebody needs to make a major
motion picture you know what amazes me
is how you're this theoretical
mathematician with such a poet's heart
well it's amazing dude but that's but
isn't so now who's getting emotional I
love it yeah I love it too and it's you
know it's about heroism it's about
violence it's about even in a tragedy
celebrating you know these are the give
the geysers I plant a task right and
like what a subtle beautiful nod to a
great life because he's not even
depicted that's you know I was gonna I
think what I'm gonna do with this show
not every not every episode is going to
be transformative and trans and
transcendent but I think one of the
things I want to do is to organize the
world and its sites for transcendence
like this Monument this this broken ring
needs to be on the map people need to
know their and they need to go on
pilgrimage yeah I've had those stories
need to be right I agree with you man
and you're you're in such a unique place
to do this I think this is gonna be a
great podcast I think I think you're
gonna love my hopes we've got so many
you know you're so interested in so many
different things and I think your look
the idea is to get the ideas the good
ideas that are stuck in books and stuck
in people's
brains who usually don't have an ability
to talk to a lot of people get them out
and into the ears and into the brains of
the people out there well and I also
want to make sure that I mean I don't
want to hide the fact that you know I'm
stuck I'm hypocritical I don't exactly
know what we're supposed to do next
either it's it's the struggle discovery
it's the despite you're trying to look
for the portals you don't know where
they all are some of them are gonna be
false leads
but transcendent you know it's what you
were saying before it transcendence is
available to everyone who's willing to
look for it it's not available in every
hour of every day well that's my
problems cancel culture because what
you're saying is you know we are who we
were we are who we are and we are we
could be and all of us are trying to be
who we could be right or at least most
of us and I'm certainly very different I
don't know the guy I don't know Brian
count the what the brain count 20 year
old Brian count 25 year old Brian what
an asshole I mean or at least what a
dumb-dumb or at least what a what a
naive is there an arrogant little
shithead I I mean I'm just a different
person now
right because I'm 52 I mean it took me a
long time to become the human being that
I am and that's pretty flawed person but
at least I'm a little less flawed made
more mistakes I have better pattern
recognition I'm a little bit more
compassionate I hope and and but you
know the we are verbs reverbs men say
more we're not nervous okay when you
cancel me out from yeah something I did
or said my god you're suggesting on that
way all the time no I'm not I might have
been having a moment I might have been
confused I was there might be a green
aura your personality
I'm sorry if you think about yourself as
a conference of different modules like
there are modules of all of us that
we're self nice some some instruments
sometimes are playing louder than the
other instrument writer that piccolo is
flat a Conner percent right and the idea
is that because of the piccolo player
the entire Symphony is cancelled I mean
I you know and who's doing this
cancelling show me one person who
doesn't have these
the vicious right I know I know exactly
and who is behind all these like it's
just the Twittersphere
right I keep hearing it's not the real
world but my problem is it is the real
world my problem is that you can lose
your ability to earn a living when
you're cancelled well so this is your
career my theory here is that we've
moved from physical violence to
reputational and economic violence
source and so the idea being that the
one thing I mean I don't know that I've
fully done this theory anywhere so it'd
be great to do it here with you it with
the the institutions have these rules on
them and these rules are causing every
institution that gets formed whether
it's a for-profit or a non-profit or in
different sectors of the economy to take
on certain characteristics the one thing
that doesn't have this this feel to it
is the individual the individual cannot
be legislated now the individual made to
be dependent on the ability to access
the banking system I mean one one show
that we have talked about is an erotic
actress who has not been able to easily
maintain merchant accounts or to gain
credit and there's a question but should
we be harassing people who are legally
employed in jobs that somebody doesn't
care for which scares that that
everybody everybody watches when nobody
else is watching you know porn stars I
mean you know if you're gonna criticize
porn stars please never watch porn well
this is the thing when I was doing these
shows with Sam Harris I would talk about
how we lie and I would say who here who
here watches porn hub and like the
audience is silent porn starts to I can
tell you everything about it not I can
even go why go through why I don't watch
it anymore it doesn't get me off so I
don't believe the girls but then I got
the girls I do believe any other
questions well this is the thing this is
what I mean because you're in it at my
salon everybody'll raise their hands
well this is the thing but because
you're an individual but then when it
comes to how you're employed yes depends
upon are you on network TV what you're
you're in cable you know what is it
we can and can't say what I believe is
because the individual is the thing that
is still free of this kind of legislated
goodness in other words there is
goodness that actually occurs and
there's goodness that is only there
because we legislated the people who
don't do not like things that are
outside of their control are going to
reputational attacks because that's the
only way of shutting down the individual
that's right and so that that
reputational violence has gotten far
more extreme for people who speak out
that's right and I think that that's
really part of the story behind you
brought up Jordan Peterson before it's
not so much in my opinion than any one
of these people is saying something
brilliant all those brilliant things are
said by some of these people it's more
that people say is there anyone willing
to stand up for central values like well
for but 60 minutes yes 60 minutes had
him on and there was the there was the
caption of English 60 minutes there was
this caption and then they did a recap
of it maybe CNN and under it said all
right professor how fucking dare well
where does this come from dare you some
asshole in control room
no but branding interviews its universe
that's not there is some story here and
I don't claim to have it which has to do
with how institutional media finds a
completely fake narrative and then just
through perseveration repeats it so
often the people think it's true well
this is why this is why fake news
quote-unquote has caught on I I'm not a
trump defender let me tell you yeah but
when I watch CNN and how slanted they
are right and and and watch these
lightweight journalists who just have
not done their homework and and they've
got three minutes or whatever it is
their their opinion pieces and stuff and
I could say the same about Fox News by
the way in a lot of cases because Tucker
Carlson drives me fucking crazy because
doesn't really listen to any of his
guests he won't even let his guests talk
but
but you know it's like it it's it's just
not true
you're not being truthful here you are
and and people know that people get it
people go hold on like when when when
Ocasio cortez calls enough Americans
racist right well the we all go we've
allowed very white Stacey majorities
very white states voted a black
president twice you're being a little
insulting here to all of us that's a
terrible thing to call a lot of
Americans I travel this country more
than she does yeah and I travel country
and I and I perform for and talk to and
I'm around real people not the elite I'm
around people that work for a living
with their hands and I can promise you
and a lot of them are white I can
promise you I promise you if you called
any of them a racist I'm talking about
people in the town so they they'd look
at you and go no I'm not no I'm not well
but you can't get out of it oh so you
deny it that just proves you know that
you are well you don't know because you
don't know where you're a well but I
guess well now what do I do
well what I really dislike about this is
that the language is so impoverished
like the issue of binary good guy bad
guy
well it exactly I mean if I'm in a
situation where I have a lot of
information about a different community
I'm gonna form positive and negative
impressions of every single possible
community but you're not but see
ideologue don't like nuance well so this
is no more a new one
well because nuance you know the way the
way I keep encountering this I've made a
big point of this they view nuance like
the Israelis view and olive grove it's a
place for snipers to hide so we have to
we have to take down the olive trees so
there won't be any snipers I haven't
piece so badly and that metaphors this
made me forget about my P which is well
we're taking a break with Bryan Callen
taking a break when we returned Bryan
Callen on the portal I've always wanted
to say this and we're back with a Bryan
Callen Bryan if we could I would love to
switch into another area that I don't
think we've really touched on much which
is your fascination with
pretty deep science and with the way in
which it even works its way into your
comedy routines and into your thinking
yeah how is it that alright first of all
I have this impression that I grew up in
LA and I used to come to some of the
comedy clubs they'd go to the improv
probably more than anything else and I'd
see comedians and they'd suddenly switch
into other languages they'd switch into
discussions of science or really
abstract discussions of history for the
material and I came to think of
comedians very often as being kind of
unregulated super mines is that
something that you think is I mean is
that I don't think so do you know where
it comes from and I've been I've been in
the business too long to think that most
most communities aren't interested in
anything but I mean no Steve Martin yeah
it's like banjo and the Robin Williams
who switch into a million different head
spaces and space I mean look at the the
I always say that I'm in the business
the one thing I that drives me is
original self-expression okay that's
what I'm interested in I'm interested in
in expressing myself fully and
originally and that responsibility is
always pretty daunting you know you want
it and so whatever it takes you know
there's there's you get to a point as a
comic where you know how to make people
laugh I can write stuff and that's a bag
of tricks then can you be thematic can
you be original can you be saying
something and that's where the real
challenge is you get older you know
writing out an hour of comedy well you
know okay
let's see what happens now what what are
you trying to talk about I mean I spent
all this time boxing and trying to stay
in shape and going beyond my biology and
being ready and you know and keeping my
home safe and whatever it might be but
there are too many flanks to cover well
what where's the funny in that you know
I'm gonna die I'm getting older and I'm
way more vulnerable than I can even
imagine so again like let's see if I can
be original about that and let's see if
I can discover something and shocked
myself and surprised myself with with my
next sixty minutes of comedy that I
guess so
unregulated super minds I don't think of
it that way I just think about probably
minutes a dysregulated oh okay yeah
dysregulated yeah III just it's a huge
privilege to belong to this very small
fraternity this small group of people
that can get up in front of anybody in
the world and make them laugh
III that's never lost on me right so I I
I feel very lucky that I can do that and
that I'm part of this small group of
people that that does that over and over
again so you have have shown like
essentially no interest promoting your
own stuff I wonder if I could just ask
you to take a couple of younger
colleagues and maybe lift them up for
our audience who should we be watching
who's coming up who you think is really
deep in terms of observation and saying
so using comedy carmichael was doing
stand-up for a long time and I think he
said he wanted to quit which is a
tragedy because he was so unique and his
success is not an accident I he was
opening for myself and a guy named of
Davidoff one of my favorite comics and
favorite people and and I just
immediately was shocked at how smart
this kid was no money I think he comes
from North Carolina and he he was Spike
Lee found him and he he did some
specials but they don't do it justice
he's just a very special guy but in
terms of sort of the younger
up-and-coming folk III I think Ali
makovski is really funny I think a guy
named Chapelle Lacey is really funny I
think I think fuck him Anwar is really
funny there are some really these are
people of the Comedy Store go to the
Comedy Store okay and on a Tuesday night
on a Wednesday night on a Thursday night
and sit in the original room mm-hmm and
I promise you you'll see some people
you've never heard of that'll crack your
ribs and and those those names come to
mind immediately just funny I mean funny
and then you got there people like
Sebastian and all these other people
that are working and have already
arrived but but yeah there there are a
lot of young people who are who are
again responding to a confusing time
right they're responding to this
confusion it's coming into the comedy
world I mean you know there's old things
you say things you can't say and I mean
jeez all right well you know I mean I
don't think there should be any rules
well I think that the rule that I like
is that the more skilled you are and the
more your comedy ultimately uplifts
people the more you not only you should
you be allowed to say but the the more
you're obligated for the rest of us to
show us how to find the humor the
absurdity and I was talking to be humor
for Christ's sake you hear stories about
people who are in hijack situation
hostage situations even and even when
even in prisoners of war they tell
fuckin jokes right so you've got man
sometimes well you know as yeah have you
ever read this short piece again by PJ
O'Rourke which i think is titled is it
serious
now and his point is lies are said with
an incredible earnestness but it is
truth that is uttered with a dismissive
giggle and I just loved this he's really
good he talks about this was Thomas
Moore you know being executed or Frigga
who and he says you know what his last
his last utterances were jokes about
make sure not to miss your mark because
I wouldn't want to create a mess or
something like that
and you know I think about that as I
tend to believe people who are kind of
smirking and giggling without being mean
about it just as is a sign of like well
hey I'm actually plugged into the
madness of all of the tensions in the
world rather than just ideologically
saying I know which way to go yeah do
you tell me about your fascination with
science what you're trying to hide and
cover up well I just think that it's
like maybe like mathematics I mean
there's a there's a there's first of all
there's a lot of people who claim that
this is scientific and things like that
and but um
I like science because at the heart of
science it seems that you start with
doubt and you continue with doubt and
and usually the though I guess I would
define science or the scientific method
as that which you can measure and that
which you can replicate under the same
circumstances I think I'm right about
that I mean to an extent at least
there's a there's a truth to that that
you can't deny well you know if you're
if you're anti vaccine please pick up a
history book you you or just a piece of
literature to see what smallpox
diphtheria measles mumps and all these
other terrible diseases did to people I
mean if you really are anti antibiotics
if you don't like antibiotics well I
don't know if you know what consumption
is but it's tuberculosis and it killed a
lot of people including Chopin and some
of the greatest minds so we've pushed
way beyond our biology and those
scientists like Fleming etc those
scientists those physicists we owe them
a great debt of gratitude the people
that invented things like the Geiger
counter and x-ray he said you know these
these and and and experimented on their
own family myth it was just thinking
about it I think it's rongkhun some
wife's hand being x-rayed there's a
giant ring on it yeah yeah you know and
then got you know leukemia or something
well you don't mercury yeah another one
you sure you know I don't know if you
know Benjamin geszti mm-hmm so this was
a like a gentleman farmer who's a
physician and he noticed that the
milkmaids
mother got smallpox right that's right
yeah and so he injected his own family
with the pus from cows to give them all
cow pox reasoning the cow pox protected
you against deadly small mark how crazy
is it that you're willing to experiment
on your family or this guy who did the
that all ulcers are not actually caused
by stress and ramaya bacteria right
Laurie or something exactly you know
this the bad ass school of science where
you actually have cured hepatitis C
which killed my cousin is that right yes
we've
cured hepatitis C Hep C is at least in
Northern Europeans I don't know if it's
still because I know interferon didn't
work at all with African Americans but
it worked with Northern Europeans to an
extent if you know the different things
you different biologies but I mean we
have I think it's a nine-month regimen
where we cure it ladies and gentlemen
cure it so I remember the AIDS epidemic
I I watched my neighbors die slowly and
without dignity I watched how horrible
that disease was I was in New York City
I was in the theater scene I was and I
was in was an acting class
I watched young beautiful men die
horribly they had car Posey sarcoma
they had lesions all over their faces
they had one thing after another I had
another friend who wouldn't let us see
him in the hospital because he was so I
went to college with him and he just he
just looked hot like he looked it would
give you trauma to look at him I watched
it I saw them die and then I saw
something called protease inhibitors
come along and these motherfuckers had
to rebuy their property because they all
sold it they had to rebuy it and now
they all live normal lives and in fact
the AIDS virus has been compromised so
often because of these different kinds
of cocktail drugs that are becoming less
and less toxic it's it's had to
compromise itself so often that it is
now something you probably can live with
like diabetes only the difference is you
don't have to take drugs because it's
become such a weakened virus that's what
happens yay-yay to Western science yiay
to science forget Western science
science doesn't belong to anybody's
along the west of the East yay - to
experimentation yay to doubt yay -
reason and compassion where Reason
serves compassion I mean this is the
thing that makes me bananas if we had
started to tell ourselves I mean I know
if you remember this one of the lies
about AIDS was that it just began in the
homosexual community and that there was
no difference between heterosexual and
homosexual transmission and that was a
an attempt at a compassionate lie yeah
but it was not actually Muslim true well
but it was also not compassionate
because the more that you told these
sort of superficial lies the less you
could actually get at who was at risk
why
well news organizations and and I read a
book about it I think it was called in
the news about the news I'm not sure I
was worth it CB s are and and there was
a lot of pressure on news organizations
to go out and find heterosexuals with
AIDS right and they combed the the
landscape for it and found a couple of
women who were straight who had AIDS
just to make sure that it wasn't just a
gay disease
well it wasn't well it but but but so
why so they couldn't figure out why it
was a heterosexual disease in Southeast
Asia in Africa but it wasn't an in North
nor in Europe in European populations in
the Middle East well why why was it also
a certain and gay men got it but in fact
the gay men that did get it were the
ones taking you know the bottoms if you
will right tops a lot of times survived
the epidemic and I know a number of them
who did it through my theater days we
couldn't figure it out it wasn't a
secondary infection was it health care
in Africa no what what happened was the
bubonic plague I think we you and I
talked about and they have what if you
survive the bubonic plague and you you
have some gene variation that developed
where you have a resistance to the
actual disease unless it's pushed into
your body with a hypodermic needle or or
somebody's dick if you were you know but
but otherwise it's gonna be hard to
contract it that's why the army couldn't
figure out they've test everybody for
AIDS and it was the the cases were slim
to vanishing and at least people that
were admittedly heterosexual right and
then we started to see that there is
something going on here that that it was
it did discriminate the disease did
discriminate not because God said it so
because there was a genetic there was a
generic genetic mutation thanks to the
bubonic plague anyway so why do I like
science I guess it gives me some answers
it's more than you like science I mean
you're pretty if you incorporate science
into your comedy yeah
and I was curious as to whether those
two parts of your brain play
harmoniously and tight I would be so
lucky you
I mean I'm not worried I'm not in your
area code in terms of your ability to
jump between the Romantics and Sun I've
never seen anything like it I've never
seen how many topics have you jumped
between this I mean you're all over the
place that no man you have a deeper I
mean your ability to movies in
literature and poetry and music and so I
actually never met anybody like that I'm
very glad you're a polymath that's how I
feel about you the the thing I was
trying to figure out though and it's
something I haven't cracked it would be
can we use comedy as a means of
delivering deeper analytic truths is
there a natural fit so for example if I
make something rhyme the brain remembers
it more easily I I set people by saying
things that rhyme are more likely to be
true and what I really mean is that when
people work out a very pithy aphorism or
or a rhyme to remember something
it meant somebody said this was
important enough to construct something
that the brain will find sticky and a
joke like almost every joke contains an
element of surprise if you saw something
it wouldn't be fun right that's right
that's right yes having answers of
course comedy is the lubrication
comedies lubricant of course look if you
want to change some of these mind as
Jonathan Hyde said yeah got it
you've got to make them feel safe you
know this is this is this is where I'd
have Sam Harris and he does a good job
for the most part but I'd have him read
the righteous mind again if he hasn't I
mean you know Jonathan Hyde's damn right
about the fact that if you want to
change somebody's mind strike some
common ground first you can't tell
somebody who's religious who because
their religion gives them meaning and it
gives them a feeling of safety right you
cannot tell them you cannot tell them
that they are like Lawrence Krauss and
people like that
you know you can't say you believe in a
fairy tale it was a book written by
peasants 2,000 years ago that makes me
really angry when people well that's
what Lawrence Krauss did on my podcast I
said Lawrence you're you are not
building a fucking bridge here dude I
mean you are you can sit there and be
right as a physicist all day long but
I mean okay cool dude I mean you're
doing zero you're doing now you're doing
a great job of destroying you're doing
nothing to persuade and destructions way
easier than persuasion it really is it's
my problem with cancellation cancel
culture etc so so this is interesting I
hadn't heard this before yeah in some
weird way and correct me if I'm wrong
there is something about the rationality
movement the skeptical movement that is
interested in cancellation of its own
but it's canceling religious culture I
think so
I I get very worried when somebody uses
the word rational over and over again
because they there are religious in
their own way they're praying to the God
of rationality I don't think that all
the answers lie there yes if you want to
figure out a way to have fresh fruit and
vegetable vegetables in the wintertime
rationality math science yes if you want
to push ourselves beyond our biology
with vaccines and antibiotics of course
but man listen listen listen don't take
my mythology away from me do not try to
take my romance I like not knowing I
loved filing I love not knowing what's
not being able to explain certain things
look it's like this if I take a piano
and smash it into a thousand pieces and
and put it in a big sack I can say this
is a piano but it's not a piano it's not
gonna be you know when it's sitting in a
corner it's a piano only when somebody
gets sits down and learns how to touch
it just so it's exactly like it was I
think it was Aldous Huxley who was
Darwin's Bulldog you know and and they
had this good-natured debate at this
this college that and and Matthew Arnold
the American you know poet / writer /
philosopher and and there was this great
debate where Aldous Huxley said you know
the we man started as protozoa and
became this pointy eared long-tailed
hominid and then we we became man and I
I have that proof because it's called
the origin of the species yes absolutely
or of there's no question that evolution
is true I believe in evolution
but as Matthew Arnold said maybe it is
true we started we started as pros /
became monkeys but there was something
about that monkey that inspired it to
Greek there was something about that
monkey yeah it created the deep and dark
writings of Aeschylus and Sophocles
Shakespeare the Parthenon Beethoven
Mozart Duke Ellington Louis Armstrong
and the list fucking goes on Eric
Weinstein and it goes on and off there
was something about that that that that
that created beauty for its own sake you
know it's that beautiful that beautiful
Schiller line man is it man is truly is
Nevermore himself than when at play and
play being defined as that thing which
you do for its own sake don't take that
shit away from me I don't want to
explain I think look it's worse than
this we are driving mysticism narrative
fiction out of science when the really
amazing science the stuff that is you
know that is like going to church is
increasingly put under pressure from the
sort of skeptic rationality community
and I skepticism and rationality super
important to both of us yeah
but there's this other impulse which is
the imaginative impulse and when you
sick rationality and skepticism on the
imaginative impulse at an early stage
you are killing the thing that built all
of the rationality to begin with
inspiration do you know what this is
this is a Klein model and the weird
thing about it is is that it only really
exists in four dimensions so this is a
model of Klein bottle technically we
would say it is immersed in our three
because this handle should not be going
through this part of the bottle and so
there's no inside and no outside it's
like I'm - Mobius band sewn together the
only reason I learned about the Klein
bottle was that I was given my father's
Xerox something in his office when I was
growing up for the National Lampoon it
was this it was a fundraiser for
terminal flatulence that looked really
official right but you showed a toilet
blown apart and you know people suffer
from terminal flatulence but it is
potentially curable it's
at the end of this crazy-like foundation
promotion fundraiser on the back page of
this thing was a short story about a
client bottle that was used as a
contraceptive device and the idea is
that it would take the sperm and send it
to the fourth dimension so no one would
get pregnant but this guy gets stucked
in the Klein bottle now this is a
completely crazy insane thing but I
never heard a clone bottle yeah and I
remember reading the story and saying
I've got to find out what that is is
that a real thing sure enough you know
there was an entire topological theory
of non-orientable manifolds and the only
way that I got to it was from a humor
magazine right yeah that's correct well
what about the idea that you're a
mathematician so I heard there's there's
a great course called the great ideas of
philosophy and it's it's in it from the
teaching company and I just quoted a
little bit of David Robinson dan
Robinson who is written more about
philosophy than anybody in the past
thirty years but he said something
interesting you talked about how you
know a theoretical mathematician spends
their whole life you know they had a
dream about some of this possibility
this mathematical possibility and they
spend their whole life coming up with
this equation that they solve and it
bears no real relevance to the material
world but then they die and okay and
thanks a lot and we have this theorem
that I guess you came up with it was
probably 300 pages long or something
like that
and then about a hundred years later or
20 years later whenever it it's used to
put a rover on Mars or something and it
does bear direct relevance to the
material world so you know again it's
what we talked about before it was like
there are certain mythologies you you
can disprove that all men are created
equal with biology and math you can
actually disprove it very easily you can
take LeBron James and send this to a
hole sends a bunch of tests but there's
a deeper truth to it when we
collectively and when we collectively
embrace this mythology this myth right
that we are all created equal it
provides a better fucking world
it provides a better cut more food on
the table more equality more diverse
more interesting culture and ultimately
a stronger culture because we're more
creative so that's a truth so so even
though I can disprove it mathematically
Obama biologically for whatever reason
this different kind of true Z it bears
sweeter fruit so one of that what if
that crazy idea thank you you've L
Harare by the way for bringing that to
my attention did you see did you see the
firt or did you hear the first terrible
interaction between Jordan Peterson and
sam Harris where's your dude okay
fighting and that's what that was
I was like Sam you know yeah you back
Sam you back to Jordan in that I I
thought they both got mired down and I
liked them both very yeah but I do think
that Sam kept putting this flag there
and couldn't move on well saying I
understood what Jordan was saying though
so let's just recapitulate for the for
the folks at so my recollection correct
me if this isn't yours is that Sam was
trying to say that truth was very
important and Jordan was trying to say
if something doesn't contribute to human
fitness then in some sense it wasn't
true little bit different so I think
what's what Jordan was saying is there
are truths that would that that there
are say scientific truths that if we
followed through with what he said was
yes we would we would extinguish the
world right and that's not a that's
that's so that that's not a truth that
so he was trying to marry truth with
Fitness is it Fitness or with with with
that well the I guess positivity
something so yeah I don't wanna be
unfair to Jordan because no I don't have
been unfair to either one of them but at
what I was looking to get was your
actual insight in something that I've
struggled with on Sam's show I said I
can reduce most of what I care about or
perhaps all of it to for different
values that compete with each other and
I said it's truth meaning fitness and
grace so there are things that are true
that Rob my life of meaning and so I
have to trade off between them there are
things that are true that might be less
fit like you discover some way of
blowing the world
that's very cheap in any high school
student could do it that would decrease
human fitness and then there are things
that are true that are not graceful that
are not beautiful that that I'd wish
were not true and well you know but you
don't need to talked about this
Nisha talked about the idea of plural
truths okay I mean when I when a chemist
looks at a painting when you look at a
beautiful painting like the Sistine
Chapel or something it brings you to
your knees right a chemist's could also
say well what you see what you think is
blue is actually not blue your eyes or
that's a trick that your eye is playing
and their bid there'd be truth to that
as well which is you take the take the
David with its famous distortions of
form Michelangelo's David only works
because it is in fact not truly a human
form it's a distorted form that is
reprocessed to be perfect right that's
right another another way to look at it
let's just take dogs for example yeah
it's true the dogs are scavengers pack
animals and hunters and it's also true
that they've probably evolved to
manipulate you with their little wags
and their ears down to the scheming
scheming they're fucking manipulating
right right okay great it's also true
that dogs are awesome yes when they die
I cry so hard I can't okay but it's not
this that's true - there's room for all
these well let's see but I don't I don't
like this I love the idea that there are
things that actually I'm willing to
sacrifice truth for so you're saying it
one way Jordan say my name say I'm
saying what I'm trying to they could
have let go of that because they would
have got they got mired down they did
and then they had that that you know I
remember Sam's agonizing should I do a
redo yeah what I get out of it then and
this is an uncomfortable place to be but
it's interesting because it's
uncomfortable to your point about what
to mine in order to get to comedy so I
maybe I'm just trying to get to a
podcast is why did you imagine the truth
was going to be a great guide to
everything else in other words why would
you imagine the truth wouldn't be
something that you might have to give up
a little bit to get a better outcome I
don't believe that the Supreme Court is
the nine wisest druids just because they
wear black robes but on the other hand
maybe I get a really better outcome if I
learn how to suspend disbelief when I go
to the
Court which I've attended once just the
way when I go to a movie yeah you know
transport me take me away make me
believe that this is in fact true yeah
yeah that's that's that's true I mean
that's that's very true there's that
there again it goes back to these plural
truths it depends on where you're
standing in the question you're asking
baby you know they're all these sort of
different variations on it but sometimes
something can be true very true for you
right then and there I mean it may make
no sense but oh I'm just having a great
time
yeah or fuck I love you yeah and then
you get linear then you have time to
think about it's like I was gonna buy
that car I asked that person to marry me
but I really felt it in the moment maybe
that's just my biology talking but yeah
I think there are different levels
they're their truths with a capital T
and they're smaller truths maybe they're
illusions but I like the illusion well I
mean I think that one of the things you
can point to just the way the way you
talked about why do people get carried
away and end up in Vegas marrying each
other is that in some sense maybe our
biology knows that we can't trust our
rational mind and that if we don't feel
swept away that one of the reasons that
these impulses are so hard to explain is
is that biology has designed this drive
to reproduce to be almost suicidal that
you're willing to sacrifice you know if
you think about it in terms of biology
you have soma which doesn't reproduce
and you have germ lines like your what's
between your legs that has a hope of
immortality and you have to make sure
that the soma is overwhelmed by the need
to perpetuate the germ and so in fact
we're born to be self-destructive and
irrational in our somatic selves because
it is our line that in some sense has to
live forever yeah you're a series of
sensations you know and you chase some
sensations and run away from the other a
lot of times I think that that's where
meditation and certainly something
that's mitosis I do because of that book
that I've always been fascinated where I
read a lot of when I was a young man I
read everything about Zen and I was very
into I was a martial arts guy and I read
a lot about you know the Japanese
tradition of Zen Zen in the art of
archery and motifs that
race and all that stuff and I even went
to my period was like the Greeks know
nothing and you know then I'm gonna
meditate it you know no that's but um
but Sam
Harris's book spirituality without
religion I really really liked because
and I really liked his app I'm not a
prank but I do it every day and I've
been doing it for almost a year now Sam
if you're out there you're welcome yeah
yeah he's he's but you guys haven't hung
out I I've never met him well let's
rectify that as I think you guys would
be I fast friend I think he's gay and I
you know to be honest I would love to
potentially explore with you some of the
issues about how to bring truly high
level math physics biology to a wider
audience I haven't really figured out
exactly I don't think you will Eric I
think that you well you know they say
that Einstein was really good and and I
it's actually I take that back
Einstein they say was really good at
explaining theory of relativity and
gravity and things to it too a
kindergartner he could use diagrams and
I think if anybody is qualified to do
that it's you because you're you you
just are a romantic dude no I'm motion
but I mean but but yeah yeah there's
such an emotional core to this stuff
right I know there isn't and and you
know when you were talking on Rogen
about how you like leaving this world
and you like you're in a world of ideas
I just I haven't stopped thinking about
it I have not stopped thinking about
what you said and and and so you are
eminently qualified to simplify these
ideas and turn them into something
beautiful if that's true and I don't
know that it maybe it's me it's a
challenge or it's a challenge but but if
it's true it has to do with a very weird
thing I think which is that symbols were
not really available to me as a language
because of my learning issues they sort
of they they play around and they jump
here and there and I can't really read
equations just the way I can't read
music and so for me what happened was I
had to find some other route up the
mountain because the symbolic route was
blocked off to me you got to make it
relevant so so why I always say to
people who are not who haven't
gone down the education road I always
say I use these little things too young
man I know how to talk to them I go
education is good you know why and they
say why go because it teaches the
difference between a good idea and a bad
idea yeah and then I say you should
study some math what the fuck math
there's nothing to listen study some
geometry algebra why why you know well
because it teaches you how to think and
they go what does that man go teach you
how to formulate an argument teach me
how to debate and beat somebody crush
somebody that's how my father did it to
me he goes it gives you ammo it'll teach
you not to be a fuzzy thinker okay any
masculine he created a masculine energy
around math guess who got an A in math
this guy and I wasn't I was always
thought I didn't have a math brain but
as soon as he did that I was like I
gotta fight the Communists I gotta have
a brain that's I gotta have a rational
mind and I got to learn how to had a you
know formulate an argument to beat that
guy in the argument I never I didn't
understand it yet I didn't I hadn't read
Jonathan Hyde yet but it's very
interesting I don't know if you've ever
read Einsteins I guess it's a it's not a
eulogy it's his celebration of plonk for
a sixtieth birthday no so he will just
you seem to have read everything
max plunk ya know Max's first night of
plug first name so yes of course plank
it's pronounced blanc so he kind Stein
said look in the in the mansion of
science you find three groups of people
he says the first is the craftsmen and
the craftsmen are largely there because
they enjoy the beauty of the
construction and the purity of it he
says then you find the competitors and
they're there because science makes for
a great game with which to beat each
other and contest I says there's a third
group which is the smallest of the three
and he said that group is the searchers
and they don't do most of the work he
said the only thing about the searchers
is that the mansion wouldn't be there if
not for them and it's just this it's
like a gambit gives you put like these
guys this is all that matters to me like
when I hear that when you just use that
metaphor but this is fuck how can you
not be a searcher the problem is that
I'll never be happy because I'm not
I'm not enough of a searcher this it's
like the great jazz musicians you ever
everything was Albert Murray who who
spoke about the difference in and you
hear this for you but that was a dog
whistle that you just pulled like the
fact that you brought up a Louis
Armstrong
yeah Louis Armstrong is captured in our
public imagination as a novelty singer
as opposed to the greatest genius that
jazz ever produced his wing like he
invented real modern jazz more almost
single-handed he could do again the
great the great ones like this like
Charlie Parker and like they would they
would they they knew their notes there
was the song and then they would go off
they would they would improv of probably
here automatically and come back to the
theme they'd find their way back I mean
that's the whole point of stand-up the
point of any kind of self-expression
living in that danger zone inspiration
doing something you didn't think you
could do you know there were that great
thing in the Karate Kid I remember when
he he breaks all the bottles and he cuts
off I don't know his first time I've
ever tried it we all want to live in
that danger zone I mean you know but gee
be a good boy player horn put it back
and go home don't be crazy you might not
find your way back you know but it's
this is what this podcast tell ya so
well Jenna thing is I want to make sure
that you can escape this as this episode
so I don't go on forever but I would
love to have you back and the thing that
would be most meaningful to me would be
to find some way for you free you and me
to explore some relatively difficult
scientific ideas together correct to see
whether or not we could make great audio
and video out of out of it because the
thing that will be most meaningful for
me is if some of the really gorgeous
stuff and you know we both are talking
about the the craft and the emotion and
the thing is is that if this doesn't end
up producing some amount of
transcendence and let's be honest most
of these episodes that I'm gonna do are
not going to get to the level of
transcendence that I'm looking for but
if we can do something to push out the
best stuff that people don't know is
there the symphonies that are sitting
there and I always make this analogy as
sheet music that is never performed like
that's how I view academic papers so
many of these things are symphonic and
they there's no public performance that
allows you to say oh that's what those
people were dealing with oh my god is
that really part of our world is that
really known and settled it's amazing
yeah I would be very moved because I
think you've got a mind like almost
nobody I've ever met in terms of range
conversational ability and the ability
to also just emotionally and in
analytically touch a subject
simultaneously without one displacing
the other bees coming from America
Weinstein that's a huge compliment but
you know I don't know but yeah I'd love
to I I would enjoy it and especially
trying to come up with is you were
talking about coming up with a
complicated will end with this but come
here with a complicated mathematical you
know it's okay you know just discussing
uh or trying to discover or talk about
you know a complicated scientific idea I
was thinking about when Socrates was
trying to prove the the existence of the
soul in the notion that we are all
immortal and have been here forever he
took the two slave voice and asked them
a complicated mathematical question and
one kid he asked a series of questions
and couldn't get the answer and another
kid they were both 11 or something and
asked him the questions and and got the
answer after led him to the answer
through a series of questions and he
said I think it was Timmy knows the
great mathematic mathematician and in
you know in Athens he said now do you
see that this boy souls not been here
long enough so he didn't have the answer
in his soul but this boy had the answer
and I just had to ask it out of him
therefore his soul has been around
longer like see so the point is we're
gonna see if I'm an old soul or young so
my guess is I'm gonna be a young so my
guess is that you are a superposition of
all so thank you my friend what a great
time guys you've been through the portal
with our friend Bryan Callen look for
his special complicated apes and if you
happen to be in the Los Angeles area or
any city Bryan's
visiting his comedy show is astounding I
think you will really enjoy it Brian
thanks for coming on the show what a
blast
[Music]